<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Agile,scrum,team,cultural-fit,scheduling,process,sprint,review,retrospective,time-boxing | Matteo Gobbi]]></title>
  <link href="http://matteogobbi.github.io/blog/categories/agile-scrum-team-cultural-fit-scheduling-process-sprint-review-retrospective-time-boxing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://matteogobbi.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-08-03T12:03:57+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://matteogobbi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Matteo Gobbi]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[job@matteogobbi.it]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Teamworking]]></title>
    <link href="http://matteogobbi.github.io/blog/2015/07/30/teamworking/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-30T23:29:42+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://matteogobbi.github.io/blog/2015/07/30/teamworking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A team, is a machine. We can imagine it like a car which goes straight ahead without issues. Like a car, it has a mechanism which should be built possibly to be bug-free. The displacement is the energy of any team member. The fuel is the passion.</p>

<p>In this article we&rsquo;ll discuss some good approach to make our team working properly and with the right attitude. Even if these approaches can be valid for any kind of team, I&rsquo;ll talk especially about a tech team, that is actually the kind of team which I work in.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><br/></p>

<h2>Cultural fit</h2>

<p>Spending most of your daily time with the same people, every day, means discussing, accepting and sharing.<br/>
Writing code in a project with other people means <strong>trust them</strong> and their skills.<br/>
So how can we figuring out if a person is the right one with who working together?</p>

<p>Hiring a person in a team is not that easy: it means investing on him, spending time to let him fully enter in the project and in all the processes. Moreover, we&rsquo;d never want to break the team&rsquo;s sinergy and happiness hiring the wrong person.</p>

<p>When I interview a tech candidate in my company, I try to understand as more as possible (and in a very short time) if he has the right technical skills and if he can culturally fit our team.<br/>
In our company we normally have 4/5 steps in which the candidate as well as getting a techincal interview, has to meet the CEO, the Product Manager and some other member of the team. When the interview is finished, we have a quick standup meeting to share our opinion with the other interviewer. Of course the priority is on the techincal point of view, as if the candidate doesn&rsquo;t rich our skills requirements, there isn&rsquo;t anything else to discuss. If instead he does, the conversation go ahead on the cultural aspect.</p>

<p>Here the truth: it is not easy to evaluate the personality of a guy in 1 hour or kind of, but if the most of us has the same impression, that could be probably true.<br/>
There are a couple of pretty funny questions we make each other in every of this meeting: <strong>would you take a beer with this guy?</strong> or <strong>Would you talk with this guy while you are waiting for your flight?</strong><br/>
They could seem 2 stupid questions, but don&rsquo;t get me wrong: these questions just help us to make concrete an abstract aspect, making easier to express our opinion. Our goal is just to understand if we&rsquo;d be happy to work with that person, and if that person would be happy to be every day with us.</p>

<p>Another good point to mention, is about the candidate&rsquo;s past experiences.<br/>
Just because a candidate used to work in Facebook, Google or any other very top company, doesn&rsquo;t mean that for sure he&rsquo;d fit our team.<br/>
Working in a small/medium company is most of the time totally different in both aspects, technical and cultural. Indeed, being the company smaller, the team could be lesser scaled, therefore the position could actually requieres more responsibilities. Moreover, being minor the quantity of employees, the cultural aspect could be much more significant.<br/>
<br/></p>

<h2>Scheduling process</h2>

<p>In the former paragraph I mentioned the importance to &ldquo;be aligned&rdquo; with the team&rsquo;s processes. A very famous software development process used in many teams, is the <strong>Agile methodology</strong>.<br/>
<strong>Scrum</strong> is an agile approach to manage a project, most of the time about <strong>Software development</strong>. I think there are few really important steps that make Scrum extremelly useful to let the team work aligned together. Let&rsquo;s see them 1 by 1:</p>

<ul>
<li>Srint Planning: estimation etc.</li>
<li>Daily Standup Meeting:</li>
<li>Backlog Grooming:</li>
<li>Sprint Review:</li>
<li>Sprint Retrospective: &hellip;Time boxing should be part of retrospective
no many company do this properly</li>
</ul>


<p>follow the scheduling on the board</p>

<p><br/></p>

<h2>Pair programming</h2>

<p>Sometimes</p>

<p><br/></p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
